relax your eyelids relax the corners of
your mouth
relax your hands pull them back a little
bit it straightens your back and your
chest comes out
and I'd like to do the breathing a
little bit different so your central
tell John John might come to a place the
opening is between your eyebrows a
little bit up from the eyebrows and this
is where the end of your central channel
comes out and sometimes when you do the
breathing meditation you can do it from
this place this hole so I would like you
to watch your exhales mom exhales but
please do it from the point between your
eyebrows groove or muddy in Sanskrit
and so you're not breathing through your
nose actually the best coming and going
to your nose but imagine that it's
coming in and out of this spot between
your eyebrows and up a few a few
millimeters and let's practice breathing
from there long exhales it will help you
to focus
and please come to your heart and make a
connection with the momma bear you can
crawl into the grain of sugar like a
little tent and sit with your llama so
you are with John and pratyahara from
the outer world your deep inside your
heart and your quiet inside a tiny space
with your teacher
and look at them make sure it's clear
the visualization as if they were really
there breathing warm fragrance
and I'd like you to think about a
Buddhist image that you are familiar
with maybe it's a painting maybe it's a
Buddha statue soaked up on Tara
Buddha coin you you choose some image
photograph painting carving something
your you see pretty often maybe it's in
your home on your alternate think about
this image try to get the details of it
in your mind what does the face look
like
what did here is the play what does the
mouth look like is it sitting with
standing don't some image to mind
I'd like you to try to imagine where was
this image made I have had some copper
statue I don't know exactly I think it
was made in Nepal but try to imagine the
person who made it or painted it or
correct it go back in time trace the
lineage of this image back to a workshop
or a studios and somebody with painting
carving
and they were using a model day they had
a different image maybe a photograph
[Music]
painting carving of an earlier version
of your image so try to go back in time
to the day your image was finished in a
studio or workshop or a factory and the
person was looking at a model on an
earlier image in my case of some copper
now go back again to the day that second
image was finished and that maybe you
have to imagine the place where maybe it
was finished we don't know exactly in my
case this metal statue the third one I
think might have been carved and I'm
just guessing or imagining maybe it was
carved and in a workshop and some very
careful
Nepalese artisan was carving a similar
image to mine three generations ago
and they're using a model and a fourth
dimension earlier image
and now skip back to the first one that
was ever made and somebody sought jetsam
kata or Tolliver Buddhas
in fact I found in an ancient art book
and they said that the first painted
image of Buddha was the Wheel of Life
and that's the great grandfather of all
images of the boomers and that was made
by someone who was looking at the
Buddhist so with your image whether it's
Tara growing in Buddha so couple let's
go back to the very first image and
someone had the good fortune someone had
the good karma to be sitting in front of
the Buddha the real Buddha or so cobbler
and someone had the ruling good karma to
sit in front of a tantric daily angel
like Tara or pointed all images of all
holy beings in this world started when
someone was looking at her thinking
about the real one
try to imagine that first sitting you
know someone's lucky enough to seat are
going in and they are trying to capture
that in a painting or a sculpture
now please come back to your image in
your home or your on your altar or your
wall the first image we started with in
my case it's at some couple nice statue
someone gave me it's under altering my
bedroom come back to that image first
one that you were thinking about and now
try to feel different about this image
its don't think Factory don't think
store think all this is a ultimately
this image started with the real person
or the real tantric barrier angel
someone saw them this statue I have is
almost like proof this statue that I
have it is the footprint of some cobbler
and it's very valuable and very rare and
I'm so lucky to have it
and then come back to the llama in front
of you thank them in your mind for this
pleasant meditation
then come back to your forehead to be
long breath from this place of focus
then you can slowly open your eyes take
a stretch
so the goal of that meditation is to
[Music]
help you keep your refuse well which one
of them yeah yeah number four so the
fourth refuge value is to respect images
of the Buddha
when I first study with my mama one of
my Jobs was to claim that temple a lot
and I got to know the temple very well
and I would he was said moved that
imaging and cleaned the altar and then I
were to grab the image by the head and
my Lama would like hit me you know okay
we can't grab some cobbler by the head
you know you have to pick him up by the
bottom you know you have to show some
respect okay so and I I'll tell you
honestly I mean it's another thing that
happens on the day you see emptiness
directly the meditation we just did
we'll have a direct experience of it you
see you you have a because you see the
Buddha directly then when you come out
when you get out your whole relationship
with images changes you know so I'm not
I'm not the kind of person that keeps a
very good altar I have friends who have
hundred images in their house and miss
doctor
if you ever go to his house it's it's
cool there's no place for people it's
all Buddhist you know I I don't do that
I just come up you have a fear and and
to be honest I don't look at them very
awesome
they just became part of my house you
know but on the day you see emptiness
your relationships to paintings and
sculptures statues it changes you get
very I don't know you feel different
about them that they almost do my life
okay and we become very they feel very
precious to you and you feel very
honored to have them okay and maybe they
will be a day in this world there will
be a day when people you know don't
remember what this image was or who it
is it's like the photographs of you you
know there will be a day than the last
one gets to another who is this I don't
know there's some grandfather's father
and they just throw it out and then the
last picture of you in this world will
be thrown out by somewhere including
someone's house you know and they say
well this guy's weird throw it out and
there will come a day in this world when
you can't get a broom you see and so
they're precious and and and one of the
parts of this vow is to be if to not
judge the quality of the painting and
not judge the quality of the stature you
know and there's a little joke it's well
there's a there's a tradition
that if you see a Buddha statue that's
not made very well you aren't allowed to
say after you take refuge in Buddha
you're not allowed to say that's an ugly
statue because we're talking about we're
goona okay so you're supposed to say the
artist was not some skills yeah so
sometimes I go with my friends can move
Lisbon don't think I don't know guess
not the artist was missing the cook was
not so skilled
that's a refuge solution so that the
goal of this meditation is to get a
bigger appreciation for the Buddha
images you have and maybe you want to
get some more and have them around maybe
you want to end up like mr. Winant know
in the monastery people give us they
give the monastery images and we have
hundreds we have too many to put in the
temple so we will rotate them and they
they bought lockers like athletic
lockers and they keep you know week
number one Locker one those Buddha's get
to be in the temple and then week number
three Locker - or dignity demon and we
it's a lot of work to change the images
and now diamond mountains dynamically I
got like ten more famous people gave me
like priceless diamond cutter sutures
and stuff there's one that rolls out
from about here to the wall I don't have
room in my house
so it's going to give it to you guys you
have to remember okay and we're putting
some at college so you're going to get a
bigger appreciation and that's part of
taking refuge okay because many many
countries have pictures of angels you
know like this one here I think it's
mimicker Berlin do you know Minsk in
munchkins
this one's Dylan yeah or maybe as Kim I
don't remember but Paris has beautiful
ones
Mexico City oh my gosh a hole sits
really in the middle of two streets
they're going into the downtown there's
I don't how many twenty thirty angel
statues
one by one on these huge pillars okay
and that's good we should be happy you
know all these churches have angels and
all these Muslim books have angels them
we should be happy it means somebody in
that country saw angel you see or met
someone who saw an angel you see so when
you see a statue of an angel in Mexico
or Germany or or Brian Ian in China you
should be happy
Oh somebody's saga okay and you should
be excited okay
now maybe I can and if you keep them
around you have a bigger chance at
senior okay all right